A Guide to the Harry W. Easterly, Jr. Papers, 1942-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Harry W. Easterly, Jr. Papers, 1942-2003
The Library of Virginia
42103
7.5 cubic feet (19 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary B. Easterly, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Harry Watkey Easterly, Jr. was born in Richmond, Virginia on 31 August 1922. He was the son of Harry Watkey Easterly, Sr. and Catherine Tighe. Easterly attended St. Christopher's School, and was a graduate of the Virginia Military Institute. He served in the United States Marine Corps during World War II. After the war, he was employed with Concrete Pipe and Products Company in Richmond, and then in the securities industry with J. C. Wheat & Company. Easterly was an amateur historian, and was also an avid golfer, serving as president of the Virginia State Golf Association and the United States Golf Association, amd he was a member of the Country Club of Virginia. He married Mary Friend Blanton (b. 1923) on 28 August 1943. Harry W. Easterly, Jr. died in Richmond on 16 June 2005, and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1942-2003, of Harry W. Easterly, Jr. (1922-2005) of Richmond, Virginia, including his research on the Westham area of Richmond, and also on George Minefee (ca. 1595-1645) of England, and James City and Charles City Counties, Virginia. The collection also contains personal files, mostly relating to his avid interest in golf.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Westham Research Files.
II. George Minefee Research Files.
III. Personal Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Westham Research Files, 1985-1995., Extent: 14 boxes. (Box 1-11, 17-19)
  The Westham research files contain information Easterly collected while writing a book he intended to publish. This series includes notes, originals and copies of published sources, clippings, correspondence, maps, and outlines and drafts of chapters. Topics include archaeology, land grants and early settlement in the area, prominent families, the James River and Kanawha Canal, churches, historic homes and other sites, foundries and quarries, and Civil War history, especially information on Dahlgren's raid. There is a substantial amount of information on Indians, including various tribes, settlements, petroglyphs, projectile points, and prehistoric artifacts. Much of this information on Indians was used in writing an article which was published in the June 1990 issue of the Quarterly Bulletin of the Archeological Society of Virginia.
  - Abstract of Title. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albion's Seed. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Archeological Society of Virginia - Quarterly Bulletin Index. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Archer, Branch - Deeds (Powhatan County). (Box 19)
  - Arnold Simcoe Raid. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bacon's Rebellion. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Banister, John - Natural History of Virginia. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beverley (Town). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Black History. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Black Swan (Magazine). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bon Air and Environs - Cherokee Road Area. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Books - Hard to Find. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brittain's. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bryan, Joe - Critique. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Byrd Genealogy. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Byrd, William II. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cabell, Kathleen. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cabells and Their Kin. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Canal - James River and Kanawha. (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Carter, Robert "King". (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Champe, John vs. Benedict Arnold. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church of England. (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Civil War History. (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - Civil War History. (Box 19)
  - Coal Mines. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Computer Discs. (Box 17)
  - Cooke, John Esten. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Custis Family. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dahlgren's Raid and CCV. (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Dahlgren's Raid and CCV. (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Dead Man's Hill. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dougherty, Jim - Critique. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Early Maps: Southeastern Coast of North America by W. Graham Arader III. (Box 18)
  - Early Virginia Families Along the James River. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Earthworks, Revolutionary. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Eight Hours Before Richmond by Virgil Carrington Jones. (Box 18)
  - England's Preparation for 1607. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - English Kings/Queens. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Falling Creek Iron Foundry. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Falls Chapel. (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - First Baptist Church, Midlothian. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The First Seventeen Years: Virginia, 1607-1624 by Charles E. Hatch, Jr. (Jamestown Booklet No. 1). (Box 18)
  - "The Descendants of Captain Thomas Friend, 1700-1760" by Carter Watkins Friend, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Genesis of the United States by Alexander Brown. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gill, John - Slides. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gillespie, Nancy Blackburn. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Goochland County. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Granite Quarrying in Virginia. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Henrico County. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Higgins, Mary Douthat Smith. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Huguenot Trail. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Huguenots. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "The Indian Rock Carvings at Westham" by Harry W. Eaterly, Jr.. (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
  - "The Indian Rock Carvings at Westham" by Harry W. Easterly, Jr.. (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - "The Indian Rock Carvings at Westham" by Harry W. Eaterly, Jr. (Sketches). (Box 19)
  - Indians - Bibliography. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Indians - Brochures, Clippings, etc.. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Indians - Chapter Outline. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Indians of Coastal and Piedmont Virginia" - Lecture, 11 October 1988. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Indians - Dighton Rock. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Indians - "The Five Monacan Towns in Virginia, 1607" by David I. Bushnell, Jr.. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Indians - Gill, John. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Indians - Indians in Seventeenth-Century Virginia by Ben C. McCary (Jamestown Booklet No. 3). (Box 18)
  - Indians - Lederer Expedition. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Indians - Marine Spring Branch Site. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Indians - Miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
  - Indians - Original Drafts. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Indians - Outlines of Various Books and Articles. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Indians - Petroglyph - Buckingham County. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Indians - Petroglyph of Arrow - G. G. Valentine Property. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Indians - Petroglyph of Arrow - G. G. Valentine Property (Sketch). (Box 19)
  - Indians - Prehistoric Art. (Box 6, Folder 3-7)
  - Indians - Projectile Points. (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Indians - Snakehead Rock. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Indians - The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography,April, 1987. (Box 18)
  - The James River Basin - Past, Present and Future. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Jamestown Artifacts. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Jamestown and Virginia's First Century - Chapter Outline. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Jewett, Jerry. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Keswick (Powhatan County, Va.). (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Land Grants - Ambler Maps and Papers. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Land Grants - Ambler Maps and Papers. (Box 19)
  - Land Grants - Benskin. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Land Grants - Beverley. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Land Grants - Burton. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Land Grants - Byrd and Stegge. (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Land Grants - CCV ("Wickhams"). (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Land Grants - Cavaliers and Pioneers. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Land Grants - Evans. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Land Grants - Historical Atlas of Westmoreland County by David W. Eaton. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Land Grants - Hudgins, Dennis. (Box 7, Folder 11-14)
  - Land Grants - Gregory, Eve. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Land Grants - Jennings. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Land Grants - King William and Queen Mary. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Land Grants - Library of Virginia. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Land Grants - Lower Tuckahoe and Tuckahoe. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Land Grants - Michaux. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Land Grants - Miscellaneous. (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
  - Land Grants - Mitchell, Mary. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Land Grants - Oslin. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Land Grants - Outline of Chapter. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Land Grants - Pleasants (Later Randolph-Tuckahoe I). (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Land Grants - Tullit, John. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Land Grants - Turff and Twigg. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Land Grants - Webb. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Land Grants - Workbook. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Latrobe, Benjamin (Virginia Cavalcade Article). (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Lee Family. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Lotteries. (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Manarin, Louis. (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Maps - Miscellaneous. (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - McCleskey, Turk. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "The Mighty James" - Richmond Times-Dispatch insert, 2 August 1998. (Box 19)
  - Mother Earth: Land Grants in Virginia, 1607-1699 by W. Stitt Robinson, Jr. (Jamestown Booklet No. 5). (Box 18)
  - Museums - Richmond. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - My Lord's Island. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - My Lord's Island. (Box 19)
  - Nicholas Family. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - The Foundry, 1952-1953. (Box 17)
  - Photography. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Pocahontas: The Life and the Legend by Frances Mossiker. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Powhite Creek. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Prince George-Hopewell Story by Francis Earle Lutz. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Randolph Family Genealogical Chart (Rolled). (Box 19)
  - Revolution, Tracing the. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - A Richmond Album by Earle Lutz. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Richmond Books - Bibliography. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Richmond to Jamestown via America's Most Historic River,1934. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Roads of Virginia. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Robinson, Jean Brydon. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - St. Stephen's Forum - Talk, 2 April 1989. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Slides. (Box 17)
  - John Smith's Map of Virginia: With a Brief Account of its History by Ben C. McCary (Jamestown Booklet No. 4). (Box 18)
  - Smyth's Travels in Virginia in 1773. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Spotswood. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Stuart's Ride Around McClellan. (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "Summerville - A Vanished Plantation". (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Talk - Neighbors, 15 January 1999. (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Talks to Groups. (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Things to Do. (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Tobacco. (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Tuckahoe Creek Canal System. (Box 19)
  - Turpin Family. (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Valentine Museum. (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Virginia Cavalcade. (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Governors. (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Virginia Historical Society. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography,April, 1986. (Box 18)
  - Virginia Place Names of British Origin. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia State Library. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Virginiana. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Westham - Latest Drafts. (Box 10, Folder 5-7)
  - Westham - Name Origin. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Westham - Outline of Book. (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Westham Project - File Index. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Westham Project - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - Westham References in Swem Index. (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - "White Hill" - Friend Home (Petersburg, Va.). (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Windsor Farms - History. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Wood, Tim. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Work Log. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Writing Techniques, Research Techniques, Motivation. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series II. George Minefee Research Files, 1998-2003., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 12-14)
  The George Minefee research files include materials used by Easterly to write an article that was to appear in the Virginia Cavalcade, until state budget cuts forced the ending of the magazine. This series contains his research notes, copies of published sources, correspondence and suggestions from the magazine's editor, drafts, outlines, and files relating to Easterly's search for an alternate publisher. Easterly eventually had the article privately published in 2003.
  - Add to Text. (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Backup. (Box 12, Folder 4-10)
  - Backup. (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Campbell, Julie 1972. (Box 13, Folder 3-7)
  - Computer Discs. (Box 18)
  - Correspondence. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Drafts. (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
  - Eckert, Madeleine. (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Family Records. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Final Draft. (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - George Minefee, Early Virginia Merchant and Landowner by Harry W. Easterly, Jr.. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Harvey Incident. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Library of Virginia References. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Marriages. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous 1969. (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Other Publishers. (Box 14, Folder 12-14)
  - Outlines. (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Colonial Records Project. (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Series III. Personal Files, 1942-2003., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 15-16)
  The personal files contain mainly information relating to Easterly's avid interest in golf, and his memberships in the Virginia State Golf Association, United States Golf Association, and the Country Club of Virginia. There is correspondence, clippings, publications, scorecards, photographs, and information on the history of golf in Virginia. Also included in this series are materials relating to Easterly's enrollment in a history course through Virginia Commonwealth University. There are class notes, exams, and thesis materials.
  - Amateur Championship - United States Golf Association, 12-17 September 1955. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Cap and Frank. (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1955. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera. (Box 18)
  - Golf. (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Golf - Certificates. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Golf - Clippings. (Box 15, Folder 8-10)
  - "Golf in the Commonwealth: A History of the VSGA and the Royal & Ancient Game in Virginia" by Bruce H. Matson. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Golf in Virginia in the 18th Century. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Golf - Miscellaneous. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Golf - Photographs. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Golf - Scorecards. (Box 16, Folder 2a)
  - Golf World. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - History 395E - Autobiography of Thomas Rutherfoord. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Hitory 395E - Bibliographies. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - History 395E - Class Notes. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - History 395E - Take Home Exams. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - History 395E - Thesis. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - "Some Early History of the Country Club of Virginia Before Its Founding" by Hary W. Easterly, Jr.. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - United States Golf Association. (Box 16, Folder 10-12)